{"tossups": [{"question": "This pope appointed Pellegrino Rossi to promote his economic agenda, which was never implemented due to Rossi's assassination. This man's election to the papacy was opposed by the Austrian Cardinal Gaisruck, but the conclave made its decision before Gaisruck's veto arrived in Rome. The Black Nobility sided with this pope, who rejected the Law of Guarantees. This pope listed eighty \"condemned propositions\" in the Syllabus of Errors. Through the bull Ineffabilis Deus, he defined the concept of the Immaculate Conception, and he oversaw the definition of papal infallibility at the First Vatican Council. This pope became the \"prisoner of the vatican\" after the Papal States were seized by Italian forces. For 10 points, name this longest-reigning pope.", "answer": "Pius IX [or Giovanni Mastai-Ferretti; prompt on Pius]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Pius IX</u></b> [or <b><u>Giovanni Mastai-Ferretti</u></b>; prompt on <u>Pius</u>]", "acceptable": ["Pius IX", "Pius IX", "Giovanni Mastai-Ferretti"], "promptable": ["Pius"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "At one point, this hero strikes an enemy with such force that his enemy is sent spinning around like a top. This hero prays to Zeus that if he dies, it at least be in the light, which causes the mist upon the battlefield to recede and reveal the corpse of his fallen comrade. This hero is chosen by lot to engage in a duel that lasts until two heralds of Zeus show up to declare it a draw. Afterwards, this hero receives a sharp silver sword and gives his opponent Hector a purple sash in exchange. This hero fights with his brother, the archer Teucer, as he provides protection with his enormous shield covered in seven ox hides. For 10 points, name this son of Telamon who shares his name with a \"lesser\" hero.", "answer": "Ajax the Greater [or Telamonian Ajax]", "category": "Mythology", "subcategory": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ajax the Greater</u></b> [or <b><u>Telamonian Ajax</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Ajax the Greater", "Ajax the Greater", "Telamonian Ajax"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This adjective is applied to a metalworking technique in which a significant reduction in ductility but significant increase in yield strength is achieved by plastic deformation, a technique sometimes called strain hardening. As a classification, this adjective denotes particles that are massive enough to move at sub-relativistic velocities, characteristically seeding small-scale structure formation, such as galaxies. A type of plasma denoted by this adjective is typically collisionless because it has zero pressure. Candidate particles for which this adjective is a classification do not include neutrinos but do include WIMPs and MACHOs. The standard model of cosmology is the lambda plus dark matter model where this adjective applies to dark matter. For 10 points, identify this adjective which, when prefixed by \"ultra\", names a field of physics that studies the behavior of atoms near absolute zero.", "answer": "cold [or word forms; or cold forming; or cold working; or cold dark matter; or cold plasmas; prompt on dark matter]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>cold</u></b> [or word forms; or <b><u>cold forming</u></b>; or <b><u>cold working</u></b>; or <b><u>cold dark matter</u></b>; or <b><u>cold plasmas</u></b>; prompt on <u>dark matter</u>]", "acceptable": ["cold", "cold", "cold forming", "cold working", "cold dark matter", "cold plasmas"], "promptable": ["dark matter"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A character with this surname is amused by the buttons on a telephone while requesting an ambulance for a resident of 244 East 87th Street. This surname is borne by a character who notes that \"history is about to crack wide open\" before ominously stating that \"millennium approaches\". That character with this surname would probably still be alive today writing for Ms. magazine if not for the efforts of Roy Cohn, who is haunted by a character with this surname while dying of AIDS in the play Angels in America. The opening line of Sylvia Plath's The Bell Jar mentions that the novel takes place during \"the summer that they electrocuted\" two people with this surname. For 10 points, give this surname shared by Julius and Ethel, who were accused of spying for the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Rosenberg", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Rosenberg</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Rosenberg", "Rosenberg"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In the film that started this genre, the protagonist uses his handcuffs to nearly beat two policemen to death, saving Mu-Mu. The soundtrack to a film from this genre features a prominent rototom (ROH-toh- TOM) break on the song \"Pusherman\". A seminal action film in this genre focusing on a plan to rescue a mobster's daughter from mafiosi was directed by photographer Gordon Parks. In addition to women in prison films, Pam Grier gained fame for starring in these movies. Following the lead of Isaac Hayes's work for Shaft, many of these films featured funk- and soul-heavy soundtracks, and they often examined issues such as drug trafficking and racial profiling. For 10 points, name this film genre popular in the 1970s, designed to appeal to African-Americans.", "answer": "blaxploitation [prompt on exploitation films]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>blaxploitation</u></b> [prompt on <u>exploitation films</u>]", "acceptable": ["blaxploitation", "blaxploitation"], "promptable": ["exploitation films"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A character in this play hides Charles Darwin's On the Origin of Species in the library's theology section so that he can finish reading it. Near the end of this play, a character spends his bus fare to have the jukebox play Sarah Vaughan's \"Little Man, You've Had a Busy Day\". A character in this play titles a prospective essay about an event of cultural significance \"A World Without Collisions\". A title character of this play is upset to learn that this alcoholic, one-legged father will be returning home from the hospital. This play begins with the black men Sam and Willie practicing ballroom dancing, and ends after the young, white Hally spits in Sam's face. For 10 points, name this short play by Athol Fugard.", "answer": "\"Master Harold\" ...and the Boys", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\"Master Harold\" ...and the Boys</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\"Master Harold\" ...and the Boys", "\"Master Harold\" ...and the Boys"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This state's Johns Committee published an anti-homosexual booklet known as the \"Purple Pamphlet\". Arthur McDuffie was killed by police in this state after a high-speed chase, leading to 1980 riots. The Save Our Children coalition was formed in this state by singer Anita Bryant to repeal a county ordinance banning discrimination based on sexual orientation. The Liberty City riots broke out in this state after the failure of then-State Attorney Janet Reno to convict police officers. About 150,000 immigrants, many from prison or mental institutions, arrived in this state during the Mariel Boatlift. Secretary of State Katherine Harris controversially halted recount proceedings in this state. For 10 points, \"butterfly ballots\" and \"hanging chads\" complicated what state's presidential elections in 2000?", "answer": "Florida", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Florida</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Florida", "Florida"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This author wrote a short story, \"At the Auction of the Ruby Slippers\", about his beloved childhood movie The Wizard of Oz. His first nonfiction book was about his trip to Nicaragua after being invited by the Sandinistas. In August 1993, this writer made a surprise appearance during a U2 concert at Wembley Stadium. This author of The Jaguar Smile wrote about his break-up with writer Marianne Wiggins and his use of the title pseudonym in the memoir Joseph Anton. Cat Stevens controversially claimed he would \"ring somebody who might do\" damage to this man if he ever ran into him. In 1991, two translators of a novel by this man were stabbed. For 10 points, name this Indian author, the subject of a 1989 fatwa calling for his death issued by the Ayatollah Khomeini.", "answer": "Salman Rushdie [or Ahmad Salman Rushdie]", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Salman <b><u>Rushdie</u></b> [or <b><u>Ahmad Salman Rushdie</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Salman Rushdie", "Rushdie", "Ahmad Salman Rushdie"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One type of this quantity is defined by assuming it equals number one, then inductively increasing its value by one every time a set is \"stretched\" such that the closure of a subset V includes every open set X containing a point. Richard Bellman coined the term for the so-called \"curse\" of this quantity, which makes solving nearest neighbor searches hard when n is greater than two. In linear algebra, the rank-nullity theorem states that the rank plus the kernel of a matrix equals this value. Fractals often taken on non-integer values for the Hausdorff form of this quantity. For 10 points, name this quantity that is the number of coordinates needed to specify a point in an object, which may be one for a line and two for a square.", "answer": "dimension [or inductive dimension; or Hausdorff dimension] ", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>dimension</u></b> [or <b><u>inductive dimension</u></b>; or <b><u>Hausdorff dimension</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["dimension", "dimension", "inductive dimension", "Hausdorff dimension"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This substance is consumed in banana mush during a ritual of the Yanomami people. Israelites who had come in contact with a corpse could be purified by this substance after the sacrifice of a Red Heifer. Worshipers of Shiva use a type of this substance to create a three-lined tilaka on their foreheads; that type of this substance is called vibhuti. In Buddhism, pearl-like beads found in this substance are treated as relics called sarira. This substance is brought to special ghats in Varanasi and spread on the Ganges River. This substance is made from palm branches, then used to draw crosses on the foreheads of worshipers on the first day of Lent. For 10 points, the first Wednesday of Lent is named for what substance that is created by cremation and wood fires?", "answer": "ashes [prompt on burnt wood, burnt corpses, burnt bones, cremated remains, or obvious equivalents]", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>ashes</u></b> [prompt on <u>burnt wood, burnt corpses, burnt bones, cremated remains,</u> or <u>obvious equivalents</u>]", "acceptable": ["ashes", "ashes"], "promptable": ["burnt wood, burnt corpses, burnt bones, cremated remains,", "obvious equivalents"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This symphony begins with a loud unison C, followed by two quick ascending figures from G back up to C. This symphony was written during the same summer that produced its composer's previous two symphonies, in E-flat major and in G minor. Its first movement introduces a theme taken from its composer's insertion aria \"Un bacio di mano\". Its fourth movement begins with first violins playing the motif \"C D F E\" in long whole notes, and introduces a total of five different themes that are later weaved into a large fugato passage in its coda. Johann Peter Salomon coined the nickname for this symphony, comparing its magnificence to that of the chief Roman god. For 10 points, name this final symphony of Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart.", "answer": "Jupiter Symphony [or Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart's Symphony No. 41 in C major; or K. 551; or Symphony No. 41 after Mozart is read] ", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Jupiter</u></b> Symphony [or <b><u>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart's Symphony No. 41 in C major</u></b>; or <b><u>K. 551</u></b>; or <b><u>Symphony No. 41</u></b> after Mozart is read]", "acceptable": ["Jupiter Symphony", "Jupiter", "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart's Symphony No. 41 in C major", "K. 551", "Symphony No. 41"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The protagonist of a drama by this author learns that the father of his intended bride has withdrawn permission for the match at a funeral, though in reality he is more concerned with the advanced pregnancy of his lover. A quote that translates as \"I myself am closest to myself\" from that play erroneously leads to the line \"Charity begins at home\" being attributed to this writer. A play by this man begins with a woman unable to go through with her promise to kill her child if it is born a girl. In that play, Menedemus drives his son Clinia into fighting in the Persian Wars after he discovers Clinia's relationship with Antiphila. Thornton Wilder based The Woman of Andros on this writer's drama Andria. For 10 points, name this Roman comedic playwright of The Self-Tormentor.", "answer": "Terence [or Publius Terentius Afer]", "subcategory": "Classical Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Terence</u></b> [or <b><u>Publius Terentius Afer</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Terence", "Terence", "Publius Terentius Afer"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A man from this city proposed an alliance at the Congress of Gela that has been called an \"ancient Monroe Doctrine\". This city was aided by the outsider Gylippus, who beat down both Demosthenes and Nicias. A king of this city suspected that a goldsmith was stealing gold he had received to make a votive crown. Legendarily a man died in this city after telling a soldier \"do not disturb my circles\", despite the orders of Marcus Claudius Marcellus. That man who lived here is said to have designed such things as a \"claw\" to shake ships and a heat ray to defend it. The birthplace of Archimedes, this city was the largest on an island targeted in a disastrous Athenian expedition during the Peloponnesian War. For 10 points, what city was the most powerful on the island of Sicily?", "answer": "Syracuse [or Siracusa]", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Syracuse</u></b> [or <b><u>Siracusa</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Syracuse", "Syracuse", "Siracusa"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A yearly \"passion play\" in this city began after an 1843 cholera epidemic and unusually depicts the harem of King Herod. That ceremony ends with the Crucifixion taking place on its Cerro de la Estrella. An image of the Child Jesus dubbed \"Nin\u0303opa\" is venerated by residents of one of this city's boroughs, whose canals are navigated by trajineras. Many tourists in this city visit a tilma, or cloth, on which an image of the Virgin Mary miraculously appeared. The largest cathedral in the Americas sits at the northern end of this city's Constitution Square, or Zo\u0301calo. Pilgrims flock to this city's Basilica of Our Lady of Guadalupe. For 10 points, name this city home to the most Catholics, as well as the most residents, of any North American city.", "answer": "Mexico City [or Ciudad de Me\u0301xico]", "category": "Geography", "subcategory": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mexico</u></b> City [or <b><u>Ciudad de Me\u0301xico</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Mexico City", "Mexico", "Ciudad de Me\u0301xico"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A value named for this phenomenon can be given in terms of temperature, salinity, and depth by four empirical formulas named for Medwin, Mackenzie, Coppen, or Chen and Millero. Governing equations of a technology that is named for, and uses, this phenomenon incorporate the directivity index as part of finding the detection threshold. A \"mushroom\" named for this phenomenon is a piezoelectric transducer made from PZT and called a tonpilz (TONE-pilts). It's not temperature, but the thermocline has a negative gradient in a characteristic value for this phenomenon, thus reflecting it. A side-scanning technology collects data derived from waves of this phenomenon with a towfish and can be used to construct a bathymetric profile. For 10 points, waves of what phenomenon are used by technology that detects objects underwater?", "answer": "sound waves [or noise; or acoustic vibrations; prompt on mechanical or pressure waves, or vibrations; do not accept \"sonar\"] ", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>sound</u></b> waves [or <b><u>noise</u></b>; or <b><u>acoustic vibrations</u></b>; prompt on <u>mechanical</u> or <u>pressure waves,</u> or <u>vibrations</u>; do not accept \"sonar\"]", "acceptable": ["sound waves", "sound", "noise", "acoustic vibrations"], "promptable": ["mechanical", "pressure waves,", "vibrations"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Software programs for creating panoramic photographs follow a rule devised by an 18th-century painter from this present-day country for rendering images with very wide fields of view. A Baroque palace in this country is decorated with a fresco depicting Cleopatra dissolving a pearl in a goblet of wine. An artist who catalogued many of this country's ruins in his engravings produced many etchings of elaborate fantasy prisons. An artist from this country painted ramshackle houses overlooking a construction site in The Stonemason's Yard, one of his many \"views\", or vedute, popular among Europeans undergoing the Grand Tour. For 10 points, name this present-day country whose 18th- century art includes Canaletto's paintings of the canals of Venice.", "answer": "Italy [or Italian Republic; or Repubblica Italiana]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Italy</u></b> [or <b><u>Italian Republic</u></b>; or <b><u>Repubblica Italiana</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Italy", "Italy", "Italian Republic", "Repubblica Italiana"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Closure and opening of a valve in this structure correspond to dicrotic notches and waves, respectively. The foramen of panizza uniquely connects left and right versions of this structure in crocodilians. This structure necessarily has the highest compliance, which is needed to lower pulse pressure. A portion of this structure is affected by a condition denoted \"triple A\" that can have a 90 percent mortality rate if it ruptures. The sinuses of Valsalva containing the origins of the coronary arteries are nestled between the wall of this structure and its namesake semilunar valve. It branches into the brachiocephalic, left subclavian, and left common carotid arteries after ascending from the left ventricle. For 10 points, name this large artery that receives oxygenated blood from the heart.", "answer": "aorta", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>aorta</u></b>", "acceptable": ["aorta", "aorta"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a play by this dramatist, a woman sings in Italian as her husband pulls her hair and threatens to stab her if she doesn't reveal who has impregnated her. In that play by this dramatist, a man declares \"the hapless fruit... hath had from me a cradle and a grave\" after he stabs a woman's womb. This dramatist created a servant who pretends to be disloyal to his master, encouraging Hippolita in a plot that ends with her poisoning herself at a wedding. This author of The Broken Heart included a scene in which Vasques stabs out the eyes of a bawdy servant in a play that details the consequences of Annabella and Giovanni's incestuous affair. For 10 points, name this Jacobean playwright of 'Tis Pity She's a Whore.", "answer": "John Ford", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John Ford</u></b>", "acceptable": ["John Ford", "John Ford"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man sponsored the Municipal Ownership League specifically to defeat Mayor George McClellan Jr. His comment in June 1901 that \"assassination can be a good thing\" hurt his standing when William McKinley was killed months later, and likely contributed to his tight loss to Charles Evans Hughes for governor of New York in 1906. This man founded Cosmopolitan Pictures to produce films starring his lover, actress Marion Davies. This man's institution produced George Herriman's \"Krazy Kat\" comic. He legendarily told Frederic Remington \"you furnish the pictures and I'll furnish the war\", in speaking about war in Cuba. For 10 points, name this publisher of the New York Journal who feuded with the New York World publisher, Joseph Pulitzer.", "answer": "William Randolph Hearst", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>William Randolph Hearst</u></b>", "acceptable": ["William Randolph Hearst", "William Randolph Hearst"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Xenocrates asserted that Plato's forms originated first as these objects. Aristotle related an account of the \"formal\" type of these objects, which cannot be combined because they are comprised of fundamentally different units. Frege's Julius Caesar problem asks how, with a certain set of definitions, we can prove that the conqueror of Gaul is not this type of object. A three-volume definitive reference edition of the works of Plato is divided into a set of these things named after Henricus Stephanus. Pythagoreans believed these things to be the first order of the universe, coming before even the elements. For 10 points, name these mathematical objects that come in real, natural, and imaginary forms.", "answer": "numbers", "category": "Philosophy", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>numbers</u></b>", "acceptable": ["numbers", "numbers"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man's father Immanuel invented a rotary lathe used to manufacture plywood as well as an underwater mine that interested Nicholas I. He wrote a play about a murderous Italian noblewoman titled Nemesis. This man kept up a correspondence with Baroness Bertha von Suttner, who is believed to have pushed him to promote pacifism. The French government accused him of treason for selling his invention of ballistite to the Italians. This man acquired the company Bofors in 1894. The line \"the merchant of death is dead\" was part of this man's premature obituary which he himself read in 1888; that obituary chastised him for inventing dynamite. For 10 points, what Swede names a series of prizes that reward scientific or cultural achievements?", "answer": "Alfred Nobel [or Robert, Ludvig, or Emil Nobel until \"Nemesis\"]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Alfred Nobel</u></b> [or <b><u>Robert, Ludvig,</u></b> or <b><u>Emil Nobel</u></b> until \"Nemesis]", "acceptable": ["Alfred Nobel", "Alfred Nobel", "Robert, Ludvig,", "Emil Nobel"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}